So I said we'd come back to that SE thing with the keyboard screen and the servers the computer within a computer
What's that there for that's the support element for the SE in order to get the mainframe all configured and ready to boot up
The way we want it to and connected everything we need to talk to that takes a little bit of a setup and you do that set up
Through the support element
There's two SEs in there and that's just in case one of them fails
No one wants to be locked out of their system now
That's all cool, but imagine if every time you needed to do something you had to walk over to the data center
Baj in hang out on the raised floor where it's all loud and cold and dark and stuff open the door slide out the SE and all that
Just to type out a single command
Luckily in addition to the SEs mainframes have this concept of the HMC or the hardware management console and these do four things
One they let you access the SEs functions remotely
So you don't have to walk out there anymore
Two you can add multiple mainframes to a single HMC a hundred of them in fact
So you can manage a whole bunch of mainframes from one HMC and that is pretty handy
You can also add a single mainframe to multiple HMCs
32 of them in fact
So if you have one system that's shared by multiple departments they can all get HMC access
For you can connect to the HMC remotely
So while the SE is attached to the system and the HMC is running somewhere else
You can also connect remotely as long as you have the correct network access
Now for the remainder of this session
I'm just going to be seeing HMC because that's typically how someone accesses those functions
But know that pretty much anything I can do from the HMC
I can do from the SE as well. It's just a whole lot easier just to say HMC
So why would we need that kind of access?
Well, the most common thing people use in HMC for is to stop, start, create and modify L-Pars
You need to add another couple processors to an L-Pars
You do that from the HMC
When it changed the way a network card is configured
You can do that for the HMC
Let's say I'm having problems with a system and I want to get some data that might help me with troubleshooting
Guess what? HMC
What do I see when I log into an HMC?
Well, I can take a look in a particular physical machine
That's this view right here
See you got the status is operating
It's got a machine type model number
It's also got a serial number
It's also got this name over here
So I can make sure it's a system that I want to be talking to
If I go deeper, I can see all the L-Pars
Those are the partitions right there for that system
Looks like some of them are up, some of them are down
That's all right
And in this last tab over here, that's the topology
That shows me how everything is connected
You can see there's lots of stuff going on over here
Another good use of the HMC is just telling me how my systems are doing
So I can see right here there's a couple of exceptions
And an exception is an unacceptable status
And it could be a problem with an L-Pars or any other object
Like a network or a crypto card
These need to be checked out right away
There's also a number of hardware messages
Now a hardware message is just when some component saw something
And it wants you to know about it
But it's not currently stopping anything from working
It's just letting you know
For example, if a fiber cable got disconnected and then reconnected
That would result in a hardware message
Same thing if an L-Pars didn't shut down correctly
Or an HMC somewhere lost connectivity
That would result in a hardware message
So what gets stored on the SC
Well, it's got code that's going to get loaded onto the mainframe
That's called licensed internal code or lick
Yeah, really
We've got logging and problem determination functions
Which help into debugging issues
Hardware systems definitions
Which basically tell the mainframe how to get started up when it first boots up
Then there's the IOCDS
Which will definitely be talking about later on
That tells the mainframe how to configure all of its I-O and its L-Pars
There's also a battery operated clock that it uses to synchronize time
Across all the components
And ethernet adapters
Because of course everything in the mainframe environment
Generally is connected to other components
So we need that
And lastly you might be thinking
So if anyone could log into the HMC
They could probably mess up a whole bunch of stuff accidentally
Right
Well yes
Which is why there are several accounts set up by default on the typical HMC
And most people set up even more to partition access
Off to those who really need it
And just because you have access to some features
Doesn't mean you have access to everything
There are specific roles on the HMC
roles like operator and advanced operator
Systems programmer, access administrator and service representative
Each one of these roles has a specific reason for needing specific access to the system
So it's not an all or nothing kind of thing
And that's the SE and the HMC
The computers within your computer
And within those computers
There's actually no there's not that's it
It's just the SE and the HMC